<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The laudable life and deplorable death, of our late peerlesse Prince Henry. briefly represented Together, with some other poemes, in honor both of our most gracious soueraigne King Iames his auspicious entrie to this crowne, and also of his hopefull children, Prince Charles and Princesse Elizabeths happy entrie into this world. By I.M. Master of Artes.</title>
            <author>Maxwell, James, b. 1581.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17701</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S126800</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847793</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847793</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12854</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07313)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12854)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1178:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The laudable life and deplorable death, of our late peerlesse Prince Henry. briefly represented Together, with some other poemes, in honor both of our most gracious soueraigne King Iames his auspicious entrie to this crowne, and also of his hopefull children, Prince Charles and Princesse Elizabeths happy entrie into this world. By I.M. Master of Artes.</title>
                  <author>Maxwell, James, b. 1581.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw: Allde, for Thomas Pauier, dwelling neere the Royall Exchange, at the signe of the Cats and parrat,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iames Maxwell.</note>
                  <note>Mostly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]²  B-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry Frederick, --  Prince of Wales, 1594-1612.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12854:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12854:1"/>
            <p>THE Laudable Life, And Deplorable Death, of our late peerleſſe Prince HENRY. Briefly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented.</p>
            <p>Together, with ſome other Poemes, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor both of our moſt gracious Soueraigne King <hi>Iames</hi> his auſpicious entrie to this Crowne, and alſo of his moſt hopefull Children, Prince <hi>Charles</hi> and Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeths</hi> happy entrie into this world.</p>
            <p>By <hi>I. M.</hi> Maſter of Artes.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Edw: Allde,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Pauier,</hi> dwelling neere the Royall Exchange, at the ſigne of the Cats and parrat. 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12854:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12854:2"/>
            <head>TO OVR LATE PEER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LESSE PRINCE HENRIES deere Brother and Siſter, PRINCE CHARLES AND PRINCESSE ELIZABETH Infants of <hi>Albion,</hi> of greateſt hope, all happineſſe.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THriſe hopefull <hi>CHARLES,</hi> gracefull <hi>ELIZABETH</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Great Britaines <hi>Hearts-ioy,</hi> Europs brighteſt beames</l>
               <l>Lo what my Muſe, though mournfull, muſed hath</l>
               <l>In laud of our late Lilly of Saint <hi>IAMES:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All Europes obiect, and the flowre of Knights,</l>
               <l>Mirrour of man-hood, wonderment of wights.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Life</hi> of him whom euery heart did loue,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Death</hi> of him whome each heart doth condole</l>
               <l>Theſe lines doe limme, while Chriſt him crownes aboue;</l>
               <l>And that his fame far flee's twixt Pole and Pole:</l>
               <l>This duties Birth I truſt ye will it take</l>
               <l>In the beſt worth, for worthy <hi>HENRIES</hi> ſake.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Of your Highneſſes The right humble Seruant:</hi> Iames Maxwell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12854:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <l>Lo heer's the Pattern of Prince <hi>HENRIES</hi> parts</l>
            <l>Of <hi>HENRIES</hi> foure the faire Epitomie,</l>
            <l>Learn'd like the <hi>Firſt;</hi> ſtout, toward, th'hope of hearts,</l>
            <l>Like to the <hi>Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> once cheife of Chiualrie:</l>
            <l>Like to the <hi>Sixt,</hi> deuoute, milde, innocent,</l>
            <l>Like to the <hi>Seau'ntn,</hi> wiſe, thriftie, prouident.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb facs="tcp:12854:3"/>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>THE MEMORABLE LIFE AND DEATH OF OVR LATE Peereleſſe Prince HENRIE.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>MANS life full well is likened to a flower,<note place="margin">Man is like a floure that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther withereth through age, or is pluckt in his Prime.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>which growing vp doth grace a Gardens aire</l>
                  <l>with ſweeteſt ſmell, but withreth in an houre:</l>
                  <l>Or elſe is pluckt for ſent, or colour faire:</l>
                  <l>Looke on theſe lines; they ſhall vnto thy ſence</l>
                  <l>Of this likeneſſe giue perfect euidence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>A plant of price they offer to thy view,<note place="margin">the ſubiect of this Legend is ſuch a flower as was not wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thred through age, but was pluckt in the Spring for the ſweetnes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pluckt in the Spring by the great Owners hand;</l>
                  <l>Of whom each flower hath being, ſhape, and hue,</l>
                  <l>And at whoſe becke they floriſh, fall or ſtand:</l>
                  <l>A flower which twice ten ſommers had not ſeene,</l>
                  <l>When it became as though it had not beene.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3<note place="margin">God carieth him ſelfe as a Gardner, or ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther as the ow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of a Garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of mortal me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, euery day as it were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſuruey of the ſame.</note>
                  </head>
                  <l>Great <hi>Ioue</hi> one day as he did walke along</l>
                  <l>Did find this flower, ſo fragrant, faire and ſweet,</l>
                  <l>This Lilly-roſe that fild all <hi>Albien</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With his ſweet ſent, he ſaid this flower's more meete</l>
                  <l>For to perfume the Paradiſe of Saints,</l>
                  <l>Then for to ſpring among earths fading plants.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12854:4"/>
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The bleſſed Angels gather vp the ſoules of vertuous men, as men doe plucke or gather ſweete flowres for their pleaſure.</note>VVhich hauing ſaid, lo troupes of Angels bright,</l>
                  <l>Poſt-haſte from heau'n, vpon S. <hi>Leonards</hi> day,</l>
                  <l>In the Spring garden at Saint <hi>Iames</hi> light,</l>
                  <l>And thence our louely Lilly fetch away:</l>
                  <l>Then home they haſte ſcaling the ſtarrie skies,</l>
                  <l>Leauing behind them blacknes, ſhrikes &amp; cries.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The Angels reioyce at the diſſolution of the ſoules and bodies of the good, but men doe mourne; the exaltation &amp; preſence of the Soule brings ſolace to the one; the Soules abſence and the Bodies corruption, brings ſorrow to the other.</note>Good Lord what diſcords were in th'accents then</l>
                  <l>Which men and Angels made with heart and voice!</l>
                  <l>Angels had ſolace, ſorrow ſeas'd on men;</l>
                  <l>Men ſigh'd and ſob'd whilſt Angels did reioyce:</l>
                  <l>Angels were glad, but men were grieued ſore,</l>
                  <l>Angels did ſing, whilſt men did ſhout and roare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>Angels and Saints in the ſupernall quire</l>
                  <l>With ſweeteſt ſongs that day did celebrate,</l>
                  <l>Bleſt <hi>HENRIES</hi> ſoule vnto great <hi>Ioue</hi> ſo deare</l>
                  <l>With heauenly Hymns they did congratulate:</l>
                  <l>With how great mirth did they this Antheme ſing</l>
                  <l>Welcome ſweer Saint the ſonne of Britains King!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The day of Prince <hi>Henries</hi> death, was both a feaſting day and a faſting day, the one to Angels, the other to men: He yeilded vp the Ghoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods hands the ſame day of the weeke, and about the ſame time of the day that Chriſt Ieſus did yeild his into the hands of his Father; to wit, on friday the ſixt day of the weeke, being likewiſe the ſixt day of the ninth moneth, when he was not full 19 years olde.</note>Deere <hi>HENRIES</hi> death thus made a feſt'uall day</l>
                  <l>T'immortall wights, to men much otherwiſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:4"/>For from their hearts all gladnes fled away,</l>
                  <l>So ſoone as he had ſhut his Eagles eyes:</l>
                  <l>VVhich made them crie, is our braue <hi>HENRY</hi> gon,</l>
                  <l>The ioy of Hearts, the Hope of <hi>Albion?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>The faireſt flowre that er'e in <hi>Britaines</hi> Ile,</l>
                  <l>Did ſprout or ſpring, or Sunne did euer ſee,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe fragrant ſmell diffuſed many mile</l>
                  <l>Fill'd Sea and Land from <hi>Wales</hi> to <hi>Virginie.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Orcades</hi> and <hi>Gades,</hi> weſt; Eaſt, both South and North,</l>
                  <l>Did ſmel the ſent which this ſweet floure ſent forth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>A wight I weene, whoſe worth both farre and neere,<note place="margin">Prince <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> piety and feare of God.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Made each eye loue him, each tong ſpeake his praiſe;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe piety, faith, and religious feare;</l>
                  <l>His fame and name ſhall to the heauens raiſe:</l>
                  <l>It was his daily practiſe twiſe to pray,</l>
                  <l>And praiſe his God; this was his vſe alway.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>A peerleſſe part in him all haue obſeru'd,<note place="margin">His admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble abſtinence from ſwearing curſing &amp; ban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>He neuer did Gods ſacred name prophane;</l>
                  <l>He neuer curſ'd; for which he hath deſeru'd,</l>
                  <l>That all ſhould ſing and celebrate his name:</l>
                  <l>To Gods bleſt word he bare great Reuerence,</l>
                  <l>And Sermons heard with humble diligence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11<note place="margin">His know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and both learned &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt diſcourſe.</note>
                  </head>
                  <l>In talking of points of Diuinitie,</l>
                  <l>Great was his wit, his iudgement and his skill;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:5"/>Men did admire the matchleſſe modeſtie,</l>
                  <l>Which did appeare in his talke euer ſtill:</l>
                  <l>Moſt father-like in his diſcourſes ſweet,</l>
                  <l>Skilfull and graue, quick, ornate, and diſcreet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">His know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Arts.</note>In euery art he had more then a taſte;</l>
                  <l>For in each ſcience of <hi>Philoſophie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He knew thoſe things that did become him beſt,</l>
                  <l>And as did ſerue his minde to beautifie:</l>
                  <l>I meane the choiſeſt things of euery art,</l>
                  <l>This peereleſſe Prince had laid vp in his heart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>13</head>
                  <l>And as he was to God deuotious,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">His loyall obedience to Father &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and his auerſenes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>Abſolomes</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring minde.</note>Reading each day his word with reuerence;</l>
                  <l>So to his parents moſt obſequious</l>
                  <l>Was he alwayes with loyall diligence.</l>
                  <l>What er'e he knew to be their minde and will,</l>
                  <l>Moſt readily he did it aye fulfill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="14">
                  <head>14</head>
                  <l>So far was he inclin'd not to rebell,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Abſalom,</hi> who helliſhly did aime</l>
                  <l>His King and father <hi>Dauid</hi> to expell;</l>
                  <l>So far I ſay was <hi>Henry</hi> from this ſtraine;</l>
                  <l>That from his Cradle to his mournfull end,</l>
                  <l>He neuer did his father once offend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="15">
                  <head>15</head>
                  <l>O happy father to haue ſuch a Sonne;</l>
                  <l>As neuer did by any wretched wayes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:5"/>So much as once prouoke his paſſion,</l>
                  <l>By word or worke! O wonder of our dayes!</l>
                  <l>The Saint of Sonnes, thus may we him enſtile,</l>
                  <l>The choyſeſt child of many million mile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="16">
                  <head>16</head>
                  <l>VVhat ſhall I ſay of the affection,</l>
                  <l>This heau'n-bred Prince did beare vnto his Brother?<note place="margin">His loue &amp; affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; Siſter.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> our <hi>Hearts-ioy,</hi> the choyſe of <hi>Albion;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhoſe towardnes doth tell he is another</l>
                  <l>Great-hearted <hi>HENRY,</hi> borne by ſtarrie fate,</l>
                  <l>This Ilands honour to perpetuate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="17">
                  <head>17</head>
                  <l>VVith what kindnes did he his Siſter cheriſh,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eliza's</hi> grace, one of the Graces three?</l>
                  <l>That Princeſſe rare that like a Roſe doth floriſh,</l>
                  <l>Filling each eye with her milde Courteſie:</l>
                  <l>whoſe happie breeding, worthy inclination,</l>
                  <l>Makes her admir'd, deſir'd of euery Nation.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="18">
                  <head>18</head>
                  <l>The great reſpect he bare vnto the Peeres,<note place="margin">His reſpect towards the Peeres, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and all Preachers.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Paſtors and Prelates, and all men of worth,</l>
                  <l>Shall be remembred of ſucceeding yeeres,</l>
                  <l>which ſhall him praiſe, and his faire parts ſet forth,</l>
                  <l>Extolling <hi>HENRIES</hi> great humanitie,</l>
                  <l>His mildneſſe and his affabilitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="19">
                  <head>19</head>
                  <l>Princes had proofe and good experience,</l>
                  <l>By coſtly preſents, feaſts and ſumptuous ſhowes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:6"/>
                     <note place="margin">His magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce towards forraine Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates,</note>Of <hi>HENRYES</hi> much admir'd magnificence,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Heroicke Heart;</hi> this thing all Europe knowes.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Spaine, Germanie,</hi> with <hi>Italie</hi> and <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In this reſpect muſt his braue Name aduance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="20">
                  <head>20</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">His grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude &amp; boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards his houſehold ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.</note>The care he had of his choyſe Seruants all,</l>
                  <l>Them to incourage and to gratifie;</l>
                  <l>Shall be ſpoke of, ſo long as euer ſhall</l>
                  <l>An houſe be kept by Prince of Britanie.</l>
                  <l>His bountie, thrift, his houſhold gouernment,</l>
                  <l>Beene marked well, they are a wonderment.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="21">
                  <head>21.</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">His great trayne and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance with his diſcretion in making choyce of wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy ſeruants to be neareſt himſelfe.</note>Seau'n hundreth ſoules his ſeruice did attend,</l>
                  <l>Which of him did reap daily maintenance,</l>
                  <l>Vnto them all his bountie did extend,</l>
                  <l>His helpfull hand, his cheerfull countenance:</l>
                  <l>Yet none were neere him, but of worthy parts,</l>
                  <l>For valour, warrefare, languages, or arts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="22">
                  <head>22</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">His great thrift in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, planting and repairing.</note>To plant and build he had a great delight,</l>
                  <l>Olde ruines his ſole preſence did repaire;</l>
                  <l>Orchards and Gardens forthwith at his ſight</l>
                  <l>Began to ſprout and ſpring, to floriſh faire:</l>
                  <l>Aske of faire <hi>Richmond</hi> ſtanding by the <hi>Thames,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If this be true; or yet of his <hi>S. Iames.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="23">
                  <head>23</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">His libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity towards Schollers.</note>His glorie was good Schollers to propine,</l>
                  <l>With large enſignes of his benignitie:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:6"/>As great <hi>Mecenas</hi> of the <hi>Muſes</hi> nine;</l>
                  <l>Which ſhall not ſuffer his braue name to die,</l>
                  <l>So long as <hi>Pindus</hi> or <hi>Mount Helicon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall be in place his praiſes to expone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="24">
                  <head>24</head>
                  <l>Likewiſe to Soldiers and to valiant Wights,<note place="margin">His bountie towards Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines &amp; Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Large was his loue, and liberality;</l>
                  <l>It was his pride to paſſe whole daies and nights</l>
                  <l>Among ſuch men, and in their company:</l>
                  <l>To ride great horſes, and to handle armes,</l>
                  <l>To heare the Drums &amp; Trumpets ſound alarmes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="25">
                  <head>25.</head>
                  <l>To Vault and leap, to wraſtle, ride and runne,</l>
                  <l>Hardly to lye, and courſely for to feede,<note place="margin">His warre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like exerciſes.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To play at Foiles, to vſe both Pike and Gunne,</l>
                  <l>Both ſword and ſhield at euery pinch and neede:</l>
                  <l>To runne at Ring, at Tilt and Turnament,</l>
                  <l>Were the delights of <hi>Albions</hi> Ornament.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="26">
                  <head>26</head>
                  <l>To learne all warre-like feats great was his care,</l>
                  <l>As for to rank a troope, to fortifie,</l>
                  <l>T'aſſige a Fort, to ſcale a wall, and there</l>
                  <l>T'erect the enſignes of braue Victorie:</l>
                  <l>T'abide heat, cold, and Souldier-like to ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>But a ſhort while, good Sentinell to keepe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="27">
                  <head>27<note place="margin">His tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance &amp; ſobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie.</note>
                  </head>
                  <l>VVhat ſhall I ſpeake of his ſobrietie?</l>
                  <l>His order'd liuing, and his abſtinence,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:7"/>His ſhunning of all ſuperfluity,</l>
                  <l>In diet, drinke, apparrell, and expenſe.</l>
                  <l>Baſe Drunkennes he hated as the Deuil,</l>
                  <l>So did he Sloath the ſchoole-miſtris of Euill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="28">
                  <head>28</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">His conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie.</note>With wine or <hi>Venus</hi> neuer was defil'd,</l>
                  <l>The Roſie body of this worthy wight,</l>
                  <l>VVith luſts allurements was he ne're beguil'd;</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Eguatius &amp; Cuſpinianus de Caeſaribus in Henrice San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto.</note>But pure and chaſte remain'd both day and night:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>HENRY</hi> the Saint that worthy Emperour,</l>
                  <l>Was not more chaſte, then <hi>HENRY Britaines</hi> floure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="29">
                  <head>29</head>
                  <l>A wondrous thing it is, yet very ſure,</l>
                  <l>That ſuch a Prince ſhould liue ſo continent,</l>
                  <l>VVhere were ſo many obiects to allure</l>
                  <l>His eyes and eares, his ſenſes to inchant:</l>
                  <l>Sith then this Soule ſo chaſte was and diuine,</l>
                  <l>Let all chaſte hands heape Roſes on his ſhrine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="30">
                  <head>30</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Scotland hath brought forth but tvvo prince <hi>Henries,</hi> and both of them were of moſt vertuous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and died young before their Fathers: the firſt Prince Henrie was the gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d child of holy queen <hi>Margeret,</hi> el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt daughter of Prince <hi>Edward</hi> the outlavv ſonne and heire of Edmond Iron-ſide King of England<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The ſecond and laſt Prince Henrie was the great great grand-childe of Queene Margarete, the eldeſt daughter of Henrie the ſeauenth King of England. Reade hereof the Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of both Countries.</note>Two hopefull <hi>HENRIES</hi> much admir'd for worth,</l>
                  <l>The clime of Scotland heertofore hath bred,</l>
                  <l>The choiſeſt floures that euer ſoile brought forth;</l>
                  <l>Both's fate it was to make this Ile to ſhed</l>
                  <l>Huge ſtreames of tears, for that in youthfull Prime</l>
                  <l>Such wights of worth ſhould fall before their time.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="31">
                  <head>31</head>
                  <l>The firſt Prince <hi>Henry</hi> was Saint <hi>Dauids</hi> childe,</l>
                  <l>That peerleſſe Prince borne of Saint <hi>Margaret,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:7"/>And King <hi>Malcolme;</hi> which of this ſeuer'd Ile</l>
                  <l>By birth did both the Royall bloods vnite:</l>
                  <l>The next did likewiſe from a <hi>Margaret</hi> ſpring,</l>
                  <l>The Gemme of <hi>Iames</hi> our Iles vniting King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="32">
                  <head>32</head>
                  <l>Likewiſe that Sainted Prince of <hi>Hungarie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Munsterus in Hugaria Auentinus in Annalibus Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iorum. Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Bonfinius Michael Riti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us de rebus Hungarie, in S. Stephano &amp; Emerico. Cuſpinianus in Henrico ſancto. Saint Henry Emeric <hi>Prince of</hi> Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie <hi>died yong and before his Father, as did our</hi> Henry Frederick <hi>Prince of</hi> Britannie.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>King ſaint <hi>Steuens</hi> Son, nam'd <hi>HENRY EMERICK</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That holy Prince did in his ſpring-time die;</l>
                  <l>As did our hearts-ioy <hi>HENRY FRIDERICK:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe holy life ſhall get him laſting praiſe,</l>
                  <l>And him enſtile the wonder of our dayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="33">
                  <head>33</head>
                  <l>Ten dayes did laſt lou'd <hi>Henries</hi> hid diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>During which ſpace, his heau'n-bred breſt did burne</l>
                  <l>With diuine loue; in God was all his Eaſe;</l>
                  <l>Mediciners could do no more, but mourne.</l>
                  <l>And good cauſe why; ſeeing their Phiſicke-art,</l>
                  <l>No help could giue to heale great <hi>Britaines Heart.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="34">
                  <head>34</head>
                  <l>Thus in the month that martyr'd <hi>Edmond</hi> fell,<note place="margin">In the month of Nouember <hi>Saint Edmond</hi> King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſuffered his Martyrdome, and both king <hi>Henrie</hi> the 3. and our peere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Prince <hi>Henrie</hi> did die, the one leauing his Kingdome to <hi>Edward</hi> the 1. the other his Prince-dome to <hi>Charles the</hi> 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Once Englands King, whoſe faith him made a Saint:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> our hope, who did in faith excell,</l>
                  <l>In hope, and loue, his holy ſoule vp ſent.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:8"/>To <hi>Chriſts</hi> owne Court; a ſoule ſo full of grace,</l>
                  <l>That it was worthy of no lower place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="35">
                  <head>35</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <p>Ado Treui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renſis in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrolog. &amp; alii plures.</p>
                        <p>S. Leonard <hi>was a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, and</hi> St. Felix <hi>a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </note>Saint <hi>Leonards</hi> day neere <hi>t' All Saints</hi> was his laſt,</l>
                  <l>That's likewiſe nam'd Saint <hi>Felixs</hi> martyr-day;</l>
                  <l>Saint <hi>Iames</hi> they call the place from whence he paſt,</l>
                  <l>In th'armes of Saints to liue with Saints for aye:</l>
                  <l>Thus Perſons, Times, and places circumſtance,</l>
                  <l>Do <hi>HENRIES</hi> Soules Saints-honour all aduance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="36">
                  <head>36</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Prince <hi>Henry</hi> a bright ſtarre ſoone Ecclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note>Lo Norths bright Star thus hath of late gone downe</l>
                  <l>In the South-point of this vnited Land:</l>
                  <l>His too ſwift courſe hath made him ſet too ſoone,</l>
                  <l>VVhen as his beames did blaſe o're ſea and ſand.</l>
                  <l>Our Orbe too baſe it was this Starre to beare;</l>
                  <l>For it was worthy of an higher ſpheare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="37">
                  <head>37</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Prince <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> a rare Pearl ſoone loſt.</note>Lo the rare Pearle, that we of late haue loſt,</l>
                  <l>A peerleſſe Pearle, the Load-ſtone of this Ile;</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe worth did drawe from euery land and coaſt,</l>
                  <l>The eyes of ſtrangers many thouſand mile:</l>
                  <l>But this heart-drawing ſtone great <hi>Iames</hi> his Gem</l>
                  <l>More worthy was t'adorne <hi>Ioues</hi> Diadem.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="38">
                  <head>38</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Prince <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> a faire flour ſoone pluckt.</note>Lo how the fragrant Lilly of this land,</l>
                  <l>The hands of Angels haue pluckt vp in haſte,</l>
                  <l>Preſenting it into <hi>Iehouah's</hi> hand;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:8"/>For this Roſe-Lilly did become him beſt:</l>
                  <l>Saints Paradiſe good Lord how it adornes!</l>
                  <l>where floures are free from thiſtles &amp; from thorns.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="39">
                  <head>39</head>
                  <l>A Starre, a Pearle, a Flowre ſith we haue loſt,</l>
                  <l>Bright, rare, and faire, if we haue cauſe to mourne</l>
                  <l>God wote, man wote;<note place="margin">Prince <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> aliue the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of hearts; but dead, the ſorrowe of hearts.</note> loe that which cheer'd vs moſt</l>
                  <l>Now doth it to our greateſt ſorrow turne:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>HENRIE</hi> aliue did lighten euery part</l>
                  <l>But <hi>HENRIE</hi> dead ſends ſorrow to each heart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="40">
                  <head>40</head>
                  <l>One thing there is our ſorrow may aſſwage<note place="margin">Prince <hi>Charles</hi> is like a <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix</hi> riſen out of Prince <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Phoenix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinder,</hi> to bee a Cordiall and comfort to our hearts.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And heale our heart-breake, which is, when we ſee</l>
                  <l>Heau'n-fauord <hi>Charles</hi> of ſuch hope in prime age</l>
                  <l>Borne to prolong this Ilands vnitie:</l>
                  <l>So oft as I behold braue <hi>HENRIES</hi> brother,</l>
                  <l>Me thincks I ſee a <hi>Phoenix</hi> from his Cinder.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="41">
                  <head>41</head>
                  <l>Looke on his face,<note place="margin">Prince <hi>Charls</hi> the viue reſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of Prince <hi>Henries</hi> both body &amp; mind.</note> and ſurely ye ſhall ſee</l>
                  <l>How <hi>HENRIES</hi> face in <hi>Charles</hi> his doth reuiue;</l>
                  <l>Marke then his grace, wit, mildneſſe, modeſtie,</l>
                  <l>And all the goods, which God doth to him giue:</l>
                  <l>Ye'le ſay with me, that there was ne're another</l>
                  <l>More like to one, then <hi>Charles</hi> is to his brother.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="42">
                  <head>42</head>
                  <l>Marke but his courage when he runnes at Ring,<note place="margin">Prince <hi>Charls</hi> his gracefull and vertuous inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, &amp; cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, godly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, wit and vnderſtanding euen in his youthfull age of 12. yeeres.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>His towardneſſe and his dexteritie,</l>
                  <l>VVhich promiſeth that he ſhall honor bring</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:9"/>One day by his braue acts to Brittannie:</l>
                  <l>Ye'le wiſh vnto this tender toward Knight</l>
                  <l>Long for to liue in health, wealth, honors hight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="43">
                  <head>43</head>
                  <l>Marke th'vnderſtanding of his youthfull prime,</l>
                  <l>His anſwers quicke, his wit, his memorie,</l>
                  <l>VVhen any Chapter of the Booke diuine</l>
                  <l>He reads, or any humaine hiſtorie:</l>
                  <l>Ye'le wonder with me to heare him rehearſe</l>
                  <l>The ſumme and ſenſe of each leafe, page, or verſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="44">
                  <head>44</head>
                  <l>Brittans bleſſe God for ſuch a toward youth</l>
                  <l>As doth ſucceede in our braue <hi>HENRIES</hi> place,</l>
                  <l>Pray vnto God for him with mind and mouth,</l>
                  <l>VViſh him alwaies the heape of hap and grace;</l>
                  <l>That ſweet <hi>CHARLES</hi> may for euer flouriſh till</l>
                  <l>That great <hi>Charles</hi> chaire with honors hight he fill.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="epitaph">
               <pb facs="tcp:12854:9"/>
               <head>PEERELESSE PRINCE <hi>HENRIES</hi> Epitaph in his owne foure <hi>Languages.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1. <hi>Epitaph.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>FAire Europes</hi> Phoenix, <hi>and great Britaines bliſſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Soldiers ſolace, and the Schollars ioy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Both</hi> Mars <hi>and</hi> Muſes <hi>minion, he it is</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VVhoſe timeles death doth young and old annoy:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>HENRIE <hi>our hope, and all the worlds wonder</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>His ſoule heauen-rapt hath left vs but his cinder.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Looke how the mightie</hi> Macedonian <hi>King</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Surnam'd the great, did periſh in his prime,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Right ſo we ſee fall in his flourie Spring</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Great-hearted</hi> HENRIE <hi>long before the time;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here reſts his Roſie corps chaſt, voide of vice:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>His Lilly-ſoule perfumes all Paradice.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>Le <hi>Phenix</hi> de l'Europe &amp; la fleur de cest age,</l>
                  <l>Le ſoulas des Sçauants, &amp; des Soldats la gloire:</l>
                  <l>HENRY ce ieun' Heros, tant beau, braue ſaint &amp; ſage:</l>
                  <l>Cy giſt laiſſant a tous de ſon los la memoire:</l>
                  <l>Tandis que durera le Soleil, Terre, ou Onde,</l>
                  <l>Son beau nom fleurira par tous les pais du monde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12854:10"/>
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>Hîc jacet Europae <hi>Phoenix,</hi> gentiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Britannae</l>
                  <l>Gloria Martigenûm, gaudia Pieridum;</l>
                  <l>Flos iuuenum, laus magna ſenum, lux alma bonorum,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>HENRICVS</hi> patriae ſpeſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> decuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuae:</l>
                  <l>Corpus habet Tumulum, famam capit orbis, Olympum</l>
                  <l>Spiritus, aeterno ſic fruitur<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Deo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>Vt perit in primo <hi>Pellaeus</hi> flore Iuuentae,</l>
                  <l>Carpitur Autumnum ſicut et ante ſuum;</l>
                  <l>Praeproperè ſic iſte ſui flos occidit aeui</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henricus,</hi> dîo maximus ingenio:</l>
                  <l>Fit Superûm conſors claro Diademate fulgens,</l>
                  <l>Linquit et aeternum Nomen in ore virûm.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12854:10"/>
               <head>A POEME, SHEWING HOW THAT BOTH THEOLOGIE AND ASTRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, doe pronounce the time of his <hi>Maieſties</hi> entring to this Crowne, to be auſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and happy.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument</head>
                  <p>AT what time God the Father entred into the world by the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation thereof, and God the Sonne Chriſt Ieſus entred into the world for the renouation of the ſame, by the aſſumption of our fleſh in bleſſed <hi>Maries</hi> Wombe, at the ſelfe ſame time <hi>Iames</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Marie</hi> entred to his new Kingdome.</p>
               </argument>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1<note place="margin">God began to make the world in the Spring-time: and about the ſelfe ſame time thereof that anſwereth to the 25. day of March accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Greeke and Latin Theologians, and all Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logians.</note>
                  </head>
                  <l>If that the time be bleſt when God began</l>
                  <l>To make the maſſe of this faire Globy frame:</l>
                  <l>Or if the time be bleſt, he moulded Man</l>
                  <l>Firſt of the Earth, for to rule in the ſame:</l>
                  <l>Then bleſt the time wherein great <hi>Iames</hi> began</l>
                  <l>T'vnite the Crownes of this great Ile of <hi>Man.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>This mother-time wherein all things were fram'd</l>
                  <l>By Gods all-working word, which was his hand,</l>
                  <l>Was fitteſt time, wherein ſhould be proclam'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:11"/>The ioyfull newes of this vnited Land:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Britaines</hi> belieue: the <hi>Worker</hi> and the <hi>Time,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of this great worke; both make it meere diuine</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">At the feaſt of the annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, Chriſt Ieſus the Son of <hi>Mary</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the world by the aſſumption of our fleſh, and <hi>Charles Iames</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Marie</hi> entred to his newe Kingdome.</note>For if the Time be bleſt God did deſcend,</l>
                  <l>From Heau'n to Earth, a Man for to be made,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Maries</hi> wombe, for vs which did offend;</l>
                  <l>To th'end mans ſinne on <hi>IESVS</hi> might be laide:</l>
                  <l>Then bleſt the time, when <hi>Maries IAMES</hi> came down</l>
                  <l>From North to South, to beare great <hi>Britaines</hi> crown.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>For at what time vnſpotted <hi>MARIES</hi> childe</l>
                  <l>Came downe from God, <hi>Eues</hi> ill race to reſcue</l>
                  <l>From death and hell, to make an vnion</l>
                  <l>Twixt God and man thus reconcil'd a new:</l>
                  <l>At the ſame time, a matchles <hi>MARIES</hi> childe</l>
                  <l>Came to vnite men with men in this Ile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Robert</hi> the 2 and the firſt of the <hi>Stewart-</hi>Kings in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp; <hi>Iames</hi> the 6. and the firſt of the <hi>Stewart-</hi>kings in England, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gan both of them their reigne in both kingdomes, at the feaſt of the Annuntiation. See <hi>Boethius, Leſlaeus, Buchananus</hi> &amp; <hi>Stowe</hi> in their Chronicles.</note>Thus <hi>MARIES</hi> time hath bene auſpicious</l>
                  <l>To <hi>MARIES</hi> ſeed, and to the royall ſtemme</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>STEWARDS</hi> name, ſprung from the valorous</l>
                  <l>Britanniſh <hi>Bruce,</hi> borne to Norths Diadem:</l>
                  <l>For in both lands the firſt of <hi>STEWARDS</hi> line</l>
                  <l>That e're bare Crowne began both at this time.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>VVhen <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſhining in his Rammie ſigne</l>
                  <l>The firſt of ſignes, and rules the head of man,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:11"/>Was running from the night-days-equall Line;<note place="margin">At what time the fun which is the prime of ſtarres, was running in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> which is the prime of ſignes, at the ſame time the prime Starre of the North by his motion began to inlighten the two Hemiſpheres of this Iliſh Orbe.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Norths bright Starre with beamie face began,</l>
                  <l>Surueying South and North both farre and neere,</l>
                  <l>For to o're-ſhine the two halues of his ſphere.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>And fit it was, that this high head of <hi>Iles,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ptolomeus, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bumazar, Fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus, Carda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> &amp; <hi>Ranzo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niun</hi> doe place vnder the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> which is the head of ſignes, the head of man which is the head of earthly creatures, and vnder the head of the ſame head ſigne called <hi>Aries,</hi> they place great Britannie which is the head of Ilands.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Britaines</hi> Ile, a royall head ſhould ſee:</l>
                  <l>T'unite her ends, though diſtant many miles;</l>
                  <l>When the head-ſigne was in his Royaltie:</l>
                  <l>Which in Mans Body challengeth the Head,</l>
                  <l>And doth his force o're <hi>Albions</hi> Iland ſhed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>Als when the Sunne did runne his Giants race,<note place="margin">At what time the Sunne was mouing in the ſigne of <hi>Leo</hi> or the Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is the Sunnes owne houſe, the Lyon of the North at he ſame time receiued the Crown of the South.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Mounted vpon the ſtarrie Lyons backe;</l>
                  <l>Then did the <hi>Lilly-Lyon</hi> ſhewe his face</l>
                  <l>In glorie great; when he the ſtile did take:</l>
                  <l>To be ſurnam'd King of great <hi>Britanie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Norths Prince of peace, and Pearle of vnitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>Yea <hi>Iuda's-Lyon</hi> that delights to feede<note place="margin">In the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation Chriſt Ieſus is called the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and in the Canticles he remaineth among the Lillies, and the Lyon enuironed with Lillies, is a chiefe part of <hi>Charles Iames</hi> his royall armes.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Amidſt the fragrant Lillies of the fielde,</l>
                  <l>Did wiſh our <hi>Gemme</hi> goodluck, (and eeke his Seede)</l>
                  <l>Which bear's a Lilly-lyon in his ſhielde;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:12"/>E'en <hi>Iudah's</hi> Lyon man-like ſweetly ſmil'd,</l>
                  <l>To ſee our Lyon, <hi>Britaines</hi> King enſtil'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">At S. <hi>Iames</hi> feaſt was hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily King <hi>IAMES</hi> crowned.</note> 
                     <hi>S. IAMES</hi> who like-wiſe was a <hi>MARIES</hi> childe,</l>
                  <l>Held feaſt that day, that King <hi>Iames</hi> bare this Crown:</l>
                  <l>Firſt on his head, as Monarch of this Ile;</l>
                  <l>Congratulate he did his new renowne:</l>
                  <l>Wiſhing that our King <hi>IAMES</hi> of <hi>Albion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Might match in hap King<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Iames</hi> King of <hi>Aragon</hi> and <hi>Valence,</hi> the firſt of that name, the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of two kingdomes &amp; both the ſon &amp; the grand-ſon of a <hi>Marie</hi> was ſurnamed the fortunate or happie: ſee <hi>Marinaeus</hi> in the 10. Booke of his Spaniſh Hiſtorie.</note> 
                     <hi>IAMES</hi> of <hi>Aragon.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>Thou <hi>Iacobs</hi> Harpe, which he holdes in his armes,</l>
                  <l>Take vp a tune out of thine owne accord:</l>
                  <l>Sing peace on Earth, and end to all alarmes</l>
                  <l>Here in the Land of thy Concording Lord;</l>
                  <l>Play <hi>Dauids</hi> Harpe, how pleaſant is't to ſee,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Britaines</hi> to liue in loue and vnitie?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Orpheus, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids,</hi> and our <hi>Iacobs</hi> Harpe is the Symbole of concorde: ſee <hi>Orus Apollo</hi> and <hi>Pierius</hi> in their Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphicks.</note>Sweet <hi>Orpheus</hi> Harp adde new ſtrength to thy ſtrings,</l>
                  <l>And tame the wild beaſts of our paſſions;</l>
                  <l>Let melodie, mounted on ayrie wings,</l>
                  <l>Charme and dechaſe our fierce affections:</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Britaines</hi> borne may liue in reſt and Loue</l>
                  <l>Vnited ay, till <hi>Chriſt</hi> come from aboue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>13</head>
                  <l>Come Prince of Peace, vnite vs all in one</l>
                  <l>In Faith and Loue, perfite vs more and more,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:12"/>Make <hi>IAMES</hi> the author of that <hi>Vnion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious workes that can enter into any Princes heart or hand are theſe two, the pacification &amp; re-union of the diuided Catholicke Church, and the reſtauration and re-union of the diuided and diminiſhed Chriſtian Empire: and it is the Authors moſt hearty wiſh, that it would pleaſe God to make the hapfull Father the inſtrument of the one, and the hopefull ſonne the inſtrument of the other.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which was amongs firſt Chriſtians of before:</l>
                  <l>And let not his braue <hi>Charles</hi> his head goe downe</l>
                  <l>Before he beare <hi>Charles</hi> or <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Crownes</l>
                  <l>Make hell-hatcht <hi>Turkes</hi> amaz'd to flee and fall</l>
                  <l>Before his face, till he be Lord of all.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12854:13"/>
               <head>A Poeme ſhewing the Excellencie of our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne King IAMES his HAND, that giueth both health &amp; wealth, inſtanced in his Curing of the Kings euill by touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, in hanging an Angell of Gold about the neck of the diſeaſed and in giuing the poorer ſort money to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the charges of their iournie.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>KIng <hi>IAMES</hi> is called of God to be the Curer of the Kings E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill; in priuate perſons corporally; in the Body of this Ile politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally; in the Pope and the whole Catholick Church Eccleſiaſtically.</p>
               </argument>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>Great King it was mine hap of late to ſee,</l>
                  <l>And to behold the vertues of your <hi>HAND;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When as from your bleſt Seate of Maieſtie;</l>
                  <l>Before Gods Prieſts, which did about you ſtand;</l>
                  <l>Your ſacred <hi>Touch</hi> did ſerue for Medicine</l>
                  <l>To ſuch as with Kings-ill had plagued beene.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>Vpon which ſight my Muſe with ſpeed began</l>
                  <l>To meditate theſe preſents in the praiſe</l>
                  <l>Of your right <hi>HAND</hi> bleſt both of God and man;</l>
                  <l>The force whereof muſt needes your honour raiſe:</l>
                  <l>Sith that the ſole <hi>Touch</hi> of it doth much more,</l>
                  <l>Then Med'cines all in curing of this ſore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12854:13"/>
                  <head>3<note place="margin">Profeſſed phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions take gold of their patients and yet oftentimes giue them not helth for their gold, but our great Phiſition giueth his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients, gold, &amp; health alſo.</note>
                  </head>
                  <l>Phiſitions, when they doe vnder goe</l>
                  <l>The Cure of this or any other ill;</l>
                  <l>Are wont to reape ſome Angels one or moe</l>
                  <l>At the ſicks hands; thus they their purſes fill:</l>
                  <l>Alwaies they take; but oft none eaſe do giue</l>
                  <l>To ſuch as doe with ſores tormented liue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>Far otherwiſe it fareth with our <hi>Leeche,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Apollo's</hi> heire, this Ilands <hi>Aeſculape;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He to his ſicke doth golden Angels reeche</l>
                  <l>Out of his hand; and makes them to eſcape:</l>
                  <l>Which makes our <hi>Leeche</hi> the Lord of <hi>Leeches</hi> all;</l>
                  <l>For health and wealth both from his fingers fall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>Queene <hi>Maulde</hi> which was great Engliſh <hi>Beauclerkes</hi> heire,<note place="margin">Polydorus Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilius. R. Holinſbed. I. Pox. I. Stow in Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And eke the Niece of <hi>Scots Malcolme</hi> our King,</l>
                  <l>Who for a time the ſtile of Empreſſe bare</l>
                  <l>Returning home, <hi>S. IAMES</hi> his <hi>HAND</hi> did bring</l>
                  <l>Vnto her Father; who to dignifie</l>
                  <l>The ſame, did found rich <hi>Readings</hi> Monaſt'rie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>S. IAMES</hi> his <hi>HAND</hi> which this faire Lady brought</l>
                  <l>Into this Land, from the imperiall parts,</l>
                  <l>(For ought I know) hath not ſuch wonders wrought,</l>
                  <l>As hath the <hi>HAND</hi> of <hi>IAMES,</hi> our King of <hi>Hearts:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The honord <hi>Hand</hi> of <hi>S. IAMES</hi> dead, I ſay,</l>
                  <l>wrought ne're ſuch Cures as K. <hi>Iames Hand</hi> this day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12854:14"/>
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">King <hi>Iames</hi> his Hand wrought an admirable, yea an incompar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cure, when he ſet together againe the Back and the Belly of this two-parted Britanniſh Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</note>Which deed of this North-South-deſcended <hi>Dame,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(For of both lands ſhe had the royall blood)</l>
                  <l>Did ſignifie, that once one of this Name,</l>
                  <l>I meane of <hi>IAMES,</hi> vnto great <hi>Britaines</hi> good,</l>
                  <l>Hauing vnited in his Body one</l>
                  <l>Both bloods, ſhould ioyne the halues of <hi>Albion.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>If dead <hi>S. Iames</hi> his <hi>Hand</hi> in place had beene</l>
                  <l>At that bleſt <hi>Time,</hi> King <hi>Iames</hi> the South did ſee,</l>
                  <l>Me thinks it would haue growne both freſh &amp; green</l>
                  <l>At the firſt <hi>Touch</hi> of <hi>IAMES</hi> of <hi>Britanie:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>E'en the reuiued <hi>Hand</hi> of <hi>S. Iames</hi> dead</l>
                  <l>On <hi>S. Iames</hi> Day had crown'd K. <hi>Iames</hi> his <hi>Head.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>O happy <hi>Britaines</hi> that thus haue in One</l>
                  <l>A iuſt, wiſe, Prince, a prompt Philoſopher,</l>
                  <l>A pregnant Poet, a Phiſition,</l>
                  <l>A deepe Diuine, a ſweet-tongued Orator;</l>
                  <l>A<note n="*" place="margin">King <hi>Iames</hi> a Prince, a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, a Phiſition, a Poet, in one word another <hi>Apollo.</hi>
                     </note> Curer both of Kings, and poore Mans Euill;</l>
                  <l>What would ye more, a<note n="*" place="margin">King <hi>Iames</hi> a Curer of Kings (if they would be cured) by wholeſome admonition, and a curer of the Kings e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill in priuate perſons by manuall impoſition, and a curer yet of another euil (which the Author calleth the poore mans euill) by bounteous ſubuention. King * <hi>Iames</hi> plaied the chaſer, yea the danter of the deuill in his voyage to <hi>Denmark,</hi> where he ſoyled al his forces and ſcattered his troupes of wicked witches in the mids of the Cimbrianeſea.</note> chaſer of the deuill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>O happy <hi>Britaines</hi> to haue ſuch an Head!</l>
                  <l>With ſuch an heart, ſuch an health-giuing Hand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:14"/>Approu'd of God, of man, of quick and dead;</l>
                  <l>Garded of Angels both by Sea and Land;</l>
                  <l>Thriſe happy <hi>Britaines</hi> I muſt needs you ſtile,</l>
                  <l>If that ye weigh Gods bleſſing of this Ile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>Bleſſe <hi>Britaines</hi> all great <hi>Ioue</hi> for giuing you,</l>
                  <l>T'vnite this Ile, ſuch a heau'n-fauord King,</l>
                  <l>Let North and South reere vp a<note n="*" place="margin">A Temple of concord or peace to the God of peace and concord.</note> Temple now:</l>
                  <l>And ioyning hearts and hands thus let them ſing;</l>
                  <l>Long liue King <hi>IAMES</hi> our Saluer and our Saint</l>
                  <l>North's Prince of Peace, Mont-<hi>Syons</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">The Oliue-tree is the ſym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bole of peace in <hi>Orus Apollo</hi> and <hi>Pierius:</hi> and our Prince of peace is like an Oliue tree planted in the Mount-Sion of the Church with Chriſts owne hand.</note> oliue-plant.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12.</head>
                  <l>And thou great <hi>Iames</hi> whom God hath bleſſed thus</l>
                  <l>With his beſt things, with might and maieſtie,</l>
                  <l>Aſcribe with heart and hand religious</l>
                  <l>All praiſe and laud vnto the <hi>Trinitie:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To Chriſts ſick Church put to your healing hand;</l>
                  <l>Cure<note n="*" place="margin">The Kings-euill of the Church is her diuiſions to be cured by the hands of kings and the heads of moderate men.</note> her kings-euil, chaſe ſects fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſten-land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>13</head>
                  <l>Play<note n="*" place="margin">The Author alludeth to <hi>Dauids curing</hi> of <hi>Saul,</hi> and his chaſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of his euil Spirit by the harmony of his Harpe. The Harpe is alwayes the Symbole of concorde, but moſt properly in our Kings perſon, in regarde of his mild moderation &amp; ſingular inclination to Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, the very crowne of all his other qualities.</note> 
                     <hi>Dauids</hi> part, our Curer and our King</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Sauls</hi> behalfe, e'en the Muſition,</l>
                  <l>With your ſweet Harpe, ceaſe not to play and ſing;</l>
                  <l>Till that ye proue Pope <hi>Pauls</hi> phiſition:</l>
                  <l>Touch ſtill the ſtrings of your <hi>Concording</hi> Harpe,</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Sauls diſcording Sp'rit</hi> from him depart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="14">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12854:15"/>
                  <head>14</head>
                  <l>But if that <hi>Saul</hi> out of his frantick moode</l>
                  <l>Pluck vp a ſpeare to pearce you for your play</l>
                  <l>Or in his fury render ill for Good;</l>
                  <l>Then grant great <hi>Ioue</hi> that one day ſee I may</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>IAMES</hi> Empyring, from S. <hi>Angels</hi> top</l>
                  <l>Reaching an Angell to the<note n="*" place="margin">The Pope (whoſe chiefe Court and chamber is in the Caſtle cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led S. Angell) is ſo ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the Kings-euill, though he will not be ſubiect vnto Kings, that he cannot be cured but by the hand of a king: and if a King on earth cannot, or will not cure him; then the King of heauen cure him for the good of his Church.</note> plagued Pope.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12854:15"/>
               <p>A Poeme, repreſenting a myſticall <hi>May-Pole</hi> of a <hi>Palme-tree</hi> from holy <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> decored with a <hi>May-Crowne</hi> of ſweet <hi>Cedar</hi> from Mount-<hi>Lebanon,</hi> and ouer-topt with an <hi>Oliue</hi>-plant from holy Mount-<hi>Sion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Preſented in hearts Earneſt wiſh on <hi>May-day</hi> being the holy<note n="a" place="margin">May-day is the comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Iames</hi>
                  </note> Day of <hi>S.</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">S. <hi>Iames</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> in <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius,</hi> and <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronymus</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Hiſtorie, is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Iuſtus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Nazaraeus</hi> for his integritie and chaſtitie.</note> 
                  <hi>IAMES</hi> the Son of <hi>Marie</hi> once the moſt holy Biſhop of the <hi>Holy-Land,</hi> ſo highly renowned for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie and chaſtitie.</p>
               <p>Vnto King <hi>Iames</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Marie</hi> Lord of the<note n="c" place="margin">Ireland is called the holy Iland by <hi>Feſtus Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>enus,</hi> ſo is Lindefarne in Northumberland by <hi>Beda</hi> in his Hiſtorie, of old the ſeate of the holy Scotiſh Father <hi>Aidanus</hi> Primate of Northumberland.</note> holy I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Simboliſing with the other both in Name and notable parts.</p>
               <p>Planted in the mids of his Spring-garden of <hi>S. IAMES</hi> there perpetually to ſpring &amp; ſprout vntill Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his hopefull hand, quicken this Conceite.</p>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>BEhold the <hi>May</hi> that home to <hi>IAMES</hi> I bring</l>
                  <l>(In hearts deſire) this day that youthfull bands,</l>
                  <l>Fetch From the fields and Foreſts flouriſhing</l>
                  <l>The talleſt Trees and boughs with buſie hands;</l>
                  <l>Their townes, their ſtreets, &amp; dwellings to decore</l>
                  <l>With Spring-times pride, &amp; fragrant <hi>Flora's</hi> ſtore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>A <hi>May-pole</hi> ſuch the like was neuer ſeene</l>
                  <l>For matters (yet vnmatcht) Excellencie,</l>
                  <l>All the <hi>May-daies</hi> that yet haue euer beene</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>May</hi> began or <hi>Mayes</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Meaning the Queene of May.</note> Mayd-monarchie:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:16"/>In no prophane place did my <hi>May</hi> firſt ſtand,</l>
                  <l>It's ſuch a <hi>May</hi> as yeelds the<note n="*" place="margin">The Palme-tree is proper to <hi>Paleſtine</hi> called commonly the holy land, ſee <hi>Dioſcrides</hi> and <hi>Geſnerus de Palma.</hi>
                     </note> holy land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The Palme-tree is the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, victorie in <hi>Orus Apollo,</hi> and <hi>Pierius.</hi>
                     </note>The holy <hi>Palme</hi> almoſt the prime of Trees,</l>
                  <l>The ſacred <hi>Symbole</hi> of prais'd patience</l>
                  <l>Was fitteſt to preſent his holy Eyes;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe patient Sp'rit all men muſt reuerence:</l>
                  <l>Milde <hi>Ieſus</hi> hauing on milde <hi>Iames</hi> his face</l>
                  <l>Engrauen the cleere Image of this Grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Aristoteles Theophraſtus, Plinius, Dioſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corides, Geſne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus de Palma.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Palme-tree is the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole or ſigne of victorie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation.</p>
                     </note>4</head>
                  <l>This Tryumph-tree the more it's beaten downe</l>
                  <l>The more it bendeth vp with matchles might;</l>
                  <l>Bowe downe his backe, behold he riſes ſoone,</l>
                  <l>Reſembling moſt a wraſtler ſtrong and wight:</l>
                  <l>Hence is the <hi>Palme,</hi> the ſigne of Victorie</l>
                  <l>Of Fortitude and Magnanimitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>In which reſpect this <hi>May's</hi> moſt fit for him,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Vertues valour doth thus vanquiſh Vice,</l>
                  <l>As Crueltie, Pride, Luſt, and <hi>Mammons</hi> ſinne;</l>
                  <l>A Victorie that mak's him happy thriſe:</l>
                  <l>As for his State, the more men it debaſe</l>
                  <l>The more God mountes it to an higher place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>Growe Princely <hi>Palme</hi> in deſpight of diſdaine,</l>
                  <l>Put forth apace your chiefe branche from your back</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:16"/>Till it o're-top <hi>France,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">To wit Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perially, for theſe words doe bear only a wiſh for the reſtauration of the diuided Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</note> 
                     <hi>Almanie</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Greece,</hi> and bring the <hi>Turke</hi> to wrack;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> helpe Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his hopefull hand</l>
                  <l>To beare the <hi>Palme</hi> through out the holy-Land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>Vpon this <hi>Palme,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A Cedar-crowne from <hi>Lebanon</hi> for our <hi>Salomon,</hi> the <hi>Samori</hi> of <hi>Albion.</hi>
                     </note> Lo a ſweet <hi>Cedar-crowne</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Fetcht from the top of loftie <hi>Lebanon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For Frankincenſe is fit for the Renowne</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch a King as aimes at <hi>Vnion:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who God-like labours to vnite vs all</l>
                  <l>In faith and loue, that vpſtart ſects may fall,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>Loe heere the <hi>Symbole</hi> of this holy peace,<note place="margin">The Oliue-tree is the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole of peace not onely in <hi>Orus</hi> and <hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Geneſis.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>An <hi>Oliue-plant</hi> his <hi>May-crowne</hi> doth decore,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſoftning Oyle bedeweth all his face,</l>
                  <l>And makes it ſweet and ſhining more and more:</l>
                  <l>Drop Oyle of peace downe from Mount-<hi>Oliues</hi> hill</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Iames</hi> his head till full <hi>Chriſts</hi> Church thou fill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>O happy ſight to ſee great <hi>Britaines</hi> King</l>
                  <l>One day deſcending from Mount-<hi>Oliuet!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O happy ſong, to heere the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> ſing!</l>
                  <l>For ioy of heart <hi>Iames</hi> to congratulate:</l>
                  <l>Bleſt be the King that comes in IESVS Name</l>
                  <l>To chriſten <hi>Iewes</hi> and Crowne Ieruſalem.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12854:17"/>
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>Great IESVS grant, that as one of the Name</l>
                  <l>of<note n="*" place="margin">More Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of peace of the name of <hi>Iames,</hi> of old, and more lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian concord at this day, of the ſame name of <hi>Iames,</hi> then of any other. <hi>S. Iames</hi> of old, did direct an Epiſtle to the diſperſed beleeuing <hi>Iewes</hi> for the furthering of their Chriſtian conuerſation, &amp; King <hi>Iames</hi> (I hope) will doe the like one day to the ſame, now misbeleeuing and more diſperſed na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the furthering of their Chriſtian conuerſion and collection: Euen ſo come Lord Ieſus, come and vnite both Iewes and Gentiles in one.</note> peace-bred <hi>Iames</hi> was the firſt that did beare</l>
                  <l>The Biſhops office in Ieruſalem;</l>
                  <l>So may our <hi>Iames</hi> that ſacred Sea vpreare:</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Iewes</hi> with Gentiles vnited in one</l>
                  <l>Next Ieſus may ſerue <hi>Iames</hi> of <hi>Albion.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12854:17"/>
               <p>A Congratulation of the moſt hopefull Prince CHARLES his auſpitious Entrie into the world,<note place="margin">Prince <hi>Charls</hi> his birth-time was both a royall time &amp; a religious time.</note> and Natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which was the 19 of Nouember 1600 being the feſtiuall day both of S. ELIZABETH the renowned Daughter of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> &amp; the Eue of the Commemoration of S. <hi>Edmond</hi> the Martyre once the moſt Chriſtian King of Eaſt-England; and the third day after the Coronation-day of the moſt renowned Princeſſe ELIZABETH our late Queene of Famous memorie.</p>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>GOe to my Muſe with mirth ſome Sonets ſing</l>
                  <l>In honor of the bleſt <hi>Natiuitie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of ſweet Prince <hi>Charles</hi> borne of a Queene and King,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Name and Fame ſhall liue in memorie,</l>
                  <l>So long as <hi>Phoebus</hi> rolling in his Spheere</l>
                  <l>Shall bring forth dayes or ſeaſons of the yeere.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>The Sunne which is the Lord of life and light<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iupiter</hi> which is called the prime of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets for felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hath his houſe and hearts-ioy in the ſigne of <hi>Sagittarius</hi> vnder which Prince <hi>Charls</hi> was borne.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To euery thing that Nature heere belowe</l>
                  <l>Doth forme or frame; when <hi>Charles</hi> firſt came in ſight</l>
                  <l>Did his bright beames from <hi>Ioues</hi> chiefe houſe him ſhowe</l>
                  <l>That day he did in <hi>Sagittarie</hi> ſhine,</l>
                  <l>Which ſtarrie wits doe call <hi>Ioues</hi> royall ſigne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>And fit it was that the beſt Planets houſe</l>
                  <l>Should Lodge the Sunne, the day ſo ſweet a childe</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:18"/>Firſt ſaw his light; an houre auſpicious</l>
                  <l>VVas due vnto the hope of Britaines Ile;</l>
                  <l>I meane to <hi>CHARLES</hi> ordain'd by ſtarrie fate</l>
                  <l>This Ilands honour to perpetuate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sagittarius</hi> is a ſigne encli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of body, quickneſſe of wit, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: alſo a certain mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall and Mercuriall ſtarre called the right ankle of the celeſtiall waineman did ariſe a litle before Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his birth, as it were to make him ready to goe to meete &amp; welcome our Martiall and Mercuriall young Prince comming into the world.</note>
                     <hi>Sol</hi> in this Signe doth frame a feature faire,</l>
                  <l>A louely face, a comely perſonage;</l>
                  <l>And doth encline to knowe all things that are</l>
                  <l>VVorthy of knowledge, to be quick and ſage;</l>
                  <l>VVhen e're theſe two the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> doe holde</l>
                  <l>They doe encline to be wiſe, braue, and bolde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>Likewiſe to be iuſt and ingenuous.</l>
                  <l>Truſtie and ſecret, conſtant, milde and graue,</l>
                  <l>Nimble of Body and laborious;</l>
                  <l>Yet ſuch a one ſhall aduerſaries haue;</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſhall oppoſe his great felicitie,</l>
                  <l>But he preuailes and gets the victorie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sagittariu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> is a ſigne maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line and encli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, beſides that <hi>Mars</hi> the planet of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, was in this manly ſigne the day of Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his birth.</note>6</head>
                  <l>To riding, ſhooting, exerciſe of Armes</l>
                  <l>Much doth the foreſaid <hi>Horoſcope</hi> encline:</l>
                  <l>Beſides that <hi>Mars</hi> who moueth all alarmes,</l>
                  <l>That day did in <hi>Ioues Sagittarie</hi> ſhine;</l>
                  <l>In ſuch aſpect as well doth ſignifie</l>
                  <l>Highnes, renowne, braue acts of chiualrie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12854:18"/>
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>Of Captaines, Souldiers and all men of warre</l>
                  <l>Beloued for his great munificence;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sagittarius</hi> is a ſoutherne ſigne &amp; hath it vnder the beſt countries of Europe, beſide the happie A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabia, and the Horoſcope in this ſigne doth encline men to goe and ſee the ſaid countries with good ſucceſſe.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>His toward proweſſe ſpreads his name right farre,</l>
                  <l>Through <hi>Sagittaries</hi> ſecret influence,</l>
                  <l>For vnder it are <hi>Spaine, France, Italie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>High-Dutch-land, Dalmace, Hungar', Arabie,</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>A happy fortune thus it doth betide<note place="margin">Sole in Sagit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tario Horoſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pante qui na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcitur paterna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haereditatem conſequetur.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVith ioyfull ſucceſſe both by Sea and Land,</l>
                  <l>A name renown'd throughout the world ſo wide:</l>
                  <l>A wiſe-bold heart with a victorious hand.</l>
                  <l>Yea more according to the ſtarrie fate</l>
                  <l>At home he muſt enioy his fathers ſtate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nouembers</hi> month into the light did ſend<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Veſpaſion</hi> and <hi>Tratane</hi> were both of them famous for their forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, courage, wiſedome, warlik prow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe, iuſtice, modeſtie, clemencie, bountie, and liberalitie, towards Schollars and Soldiours; whereof read <hi>Suetonius, Dion,</hi> and <hi>Aurelius Victor</hi> in their Hiſtories. <hi>Henrie</hi> the 4. was likewiſe a Prince of great vnderſtanding, and of quicke wit; eloquent, liberall, and in warre both foreward and fortunate; he fought more fields then <hi>M. Marcellus</hi> or yet <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> and alwayes with a victorious iſſue, whereof read <hi>Baptiſta Egnatius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Cuſpinianus</hi> in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours liues.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Three worthy <hi>Caeſars</hi> wiſe, and valorous,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Veſpaſian, Traiane</hi> the choyſe of men,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth a Prince victorious;</l>
                  <l>VVho ſixtie times did with his ſword and ſhield</l>
                  <l>Alwaies bring home great honor from the field.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12854:19"/>
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of Burgundie and Brabant, was a Prince of exceeding great magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie; and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from his loweſt yeeres, much addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to warrelike exerciſes, patient of cold and heat, hunger and thirſt, and both tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and continent, free from luxury and lecherie, and the moſt toward wight of his time, of whom read <hi>Pontus Heuterus</hi> in his Hiſtorie of Burgundie.</note>The ſame month bare Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of Burgundie,</l>
                  <l>Surnam'd the bold, a Chieftaine ſterne and ſtout,</l>
                  <l>Who many times brought home braue victorie,</l>
                  <l>And did his proweſſe proue at many a rout:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France</hi> much fear'd his force and might</l>
                  <l>And had the worſe by him in field and fight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Philip</hi> Prince Palatine of Rhine, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned for his warrelike proweſſe and ſingular wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome the was a great fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer both of Schollars and Soldiours, and was choſen Generall of the Imperiall forces, both by <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, and <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the firſt Emperors: of his proweſſe, read in <hi>Melchior Suterus</hi> Hiſtorie of the Hungarian warre: and <hi>Auguſtinus Brunnius</hi> in his Catalogue of the Palatine Princes.</note>
                     <hi>Philip</hi> the braue Prince Palatine of <hi>Rhine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For his rare courage cal'd the Bellicous,</l>
                  <l>Was borne about our young Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his time</l>
                  <l>Whom heere I name for his acts chiualrous;</l>
                  <l>Which he did ſhewe vnder great <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then Emperour, in defence of <hi>Vienne.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>Twentie ſore aſſaults <hi>Soliman</hi> had made</l>
                  <l>The famous Citie for to take by might;</l>
                  <l>Whole ſixty thouſand fell downe by his blade;</l>
                  <l>Yet forward <hi>Philip</hi> was not turn'd to flight:</l>
                  <l>But valiantly did in defending ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Till that the <hi>Turks</hi> were faine to flee their way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>13</head>
                  <l>* Great <hi>Archer-King</hi> the ſoueraigne Lord of all</l>
                  <l>Who didſt ordaine Prince <hi>Charles</hi> to ſee the light</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:19"/>In th'archer-ſigne which brings a fat all fall,<note place="margin">In the Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Chriſt is painted out as a crowned ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher riding on a white horſe, with a bow in his hand, going forth to conquer and ouercome: &amp; in Aſtrologie <hi>Caput Draconis</hi> or the Dragons head hath his fall in the ſigne of the Archer, vnder the which Prince Charles was borne to be an inſtrument one day, by his ſharpe arrowes of the Turkiſh Dragons fall and finall ouerthrowe.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>Dragons-head;</hi> ſtrengthen this tender Knight;</l>
                  <l>Guide thou his Arrow and direct his Dart</l>
                  <l>To pierce the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Dragons head and hart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="14">
                  <head>14</head>
                  <l>Stout <hi>Caſtriote,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>George Caſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ote</hi> a Prince of incomparable courage, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnanimitie &amp; ſtrength of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, entred to his Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banie</hi> in the ſouth about the ſame time that Prince <hi>Charles</hi> was borne to be Duke of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banie</hi> in the North, and afterwards ſucceeded to his brother Prince <hi>Henrie</hi> in the Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Britannie. Of the Turkes he was called <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> which is another <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, for his great valour: and of the Chriſtians, in whoſe cauſe he ſhewed an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable fortitude againſt the Turkes in many battles and fields, he was called <hi>Chrssts ſoldier</hi> and <hi>Champion:</hi> he liued in great honour reputation and fame, in deſpight of the Turkes the ſpace of 63. yeeres: of whome read <hi>Marinus Barletius</hi> in his life, <hi>Velaterranus</hi> in his deſcription of Macedonie, <hi>Aeneas Syluius</hi> in his Europe, and <hi>Paulus Iouius</hi> in his Turkiſh Commentaries.</note> whom <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> they call</l>
                  <l>A ſecond <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> valiant, bolde and braue,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Troups that often did apall</l>
                  <l>And in the field full oft the foyle them gaue</l>
                  <l>About the time of <hi>Charles</hi> Natiuitie</l>
                  <l>Began to be nam'd Prince of <hi>Albanie.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="15">
                  <head>15</head>
                  <l>O happy ſight to ſee Prince <hi>Charles</hi> one day<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Caſtriote alias Scanderbeg</hi> was Duke of <hi>Albanie</hi> in the ſouth, and our <hi>Charles is</hi> Duke o <hi>Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> in the North.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>With <hi>Caſtriote</hi> once chiefe of chiualrie</l>
                  <l>Againſt the <hi>Turks</hi> his Banner to diſplay,</l>
                  <l>That as hee's nam'd the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Albanie:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So men may him a <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> enſtile</l>
                  <l>Th'horror of <hi>Turks,</hi> the <hi>Hector</hi> of this Ile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="16">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12854:20"/>
                  <head>16</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> name our <hi>Charles</hi> of Britanie</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> thy Soldier and thy Knight,</l>
                  <l>Adde vnto his one Nothern <hi>Albanie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Six<note n="*" place="margin">In the Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphie of <hi>Ptolemaeus, Strab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, Plinius</hi> and <hi>Stephanus</hi> there doe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre ſix coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the eaſt &amp; ſouth, which beare the name of <hi>Albanie,</hi> and they lye in Greece, Arabie, Armenie, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie, and Italie, or thereabout; and the ſeauenth <hi>Albanie</hi> is in the North of Britannie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a part of Scotland, and the firſt Dukedome of Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> whome Chriſt enable to vnite them Imperially all in one.</note> 
                     <hi>Albanies,</hi> chooſe him thy fields to fight</l>
                  <l>Gainſt <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and giue him for his bire</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Towne with the proud <hi>Turks</hi> Empire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="17">
                  <head>17</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Prince <hi>Albert</hi> Marquiſe of Brandenburg for his incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable valour called the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiles</hi> of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie, was borne on the 19. of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, euen as our Prince <hi>Charles</hi> was: ſee <hi>Nicholaus Reuſnerus</hi> in <hi>Diario Historico,</hi> a briefe deſcription of whoſe incomparable valour, and magnanimitie, is to be read in the Genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall workes of <hi>Elias Reuſnerus</hi> and <hi>Hieronymus Henninges,</hi> as alſo in the Electorall Catalogue of <hi>Auguſtinus Brunnius.</hi>
                     </note>For month and day, at the ſame very time</l>
                  <l>That matchles Marquiſe firſt did ſee the light,</l>
                  <l>Who was the honor of the Germaine Clime</l>
                  <l>Whoſe name <hi>Albert Almans Achilles</hi> hight:</l>
                  <l>A Prince for fortune, courage, war-like arts</l>
                  <l>VViſedome and worth, renowned in all parts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="18">
                  <head>18</head>
                  <l>A <hi>Martiall</hi> Body, a <hi>Mercuriall</hi> minde,</l>
                  <l>An ornate Tongue, with an vndaunted heart,</l>
                  <l>Moſt happily were in this Prince combinde,</l>
                  <l>His proweſſe was ſpoke of in euery part:</l>
                  <l>Witnes his warres in <hi>Pruſſe</hi> and <hi>Polonie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>Sileſe, Boheme,</hi> and all <hi>Almanie.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="19">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12854:20"/>
                  <head>19</head>
                  <l>Many a troupe this Dutch <hi>Achilles</hi> led,</l>
                  <l>His fierceſt foes he brought them on their backe,</l>
                  <l>Of Challengers right oft the blood he ſhed,</l>
                  <l>Scal'd many a wall; and ſtrongeſt townes did take:</l>
                  <l>Was ay the firſt that enter'd in the field,</l>
                  <l>And ay the laſt that laid downe ſword and ſhield.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="20">
                  <head>20</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Albert</hi> was matchles in all martiall playes,<note place="margin">Prince <hi>Albert</hi> did 17. times runne againſt men all armed and threwe them in the duſt, he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hauing no more ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor on him except his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met &amp; ſhield.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of Iuſting, tilting, and of Tournament,</l>
                  <l>The onely man remarked in thoſe dayes</l>
                  <l>Who ne're incur'd diſgrace or detriment:</l>
                  <l>Yet he vnarm'd, did ſeauenteene times in Iouſt</l>
                  <l>Hurle men all-armd from horſe-back in the duſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="21">
                  <head>21</head>
                  <l>Yeeres ſeauentie one this worthy wight did liue</l>
                  <l>In great renowne, with honor, hap, and fame;</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Ioue</hi> to our yong <hi>Charles</hi> vouchſafe to giue</l>
                  <l>The like long life with braue <hi>Albertus</hi> name:</l>
                  <l>As oft as I ſee ſweet <hi>Charles</hi> runne at Ring,</l>
                  <l>Me thinks his Sp'rite did from <hi>Albertus</hi> ſpring.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="22">
                  <head>22</head>
                  <l>Great God of Armes grant honor'd <hi>Alberts</hi> hart,</l>
                  <l>His hand and hap to <hi>Charles</hi> great Britaines ſtay;</l>
                  <l>Grant him to proue his Proweſſe in each part</l>
                  <l>As he was borne in <hi>Alberts</hi> month and day;</l>
                  <l>Make him be nam'd th' <hi>Achilles</hi> Britannick,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Albert</hi> was th'<hi>Achilles</hi> Germanick.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:12854:21"/>
               <p>A Congratulation of the happy Birth of the moſt gracefull Princes ELIZABETH, which was the 19. of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt 1596. being the feſtiuall day of the holy Matrone and Martyr S. <hi>Thecla,</hi> and the next day after the Commemoration of the moſt religious, &amp; renowned Empreſſe S. <hi>Helen</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Coilus</hi> King of Britanie, and the Mother of the firſt Chriſtian Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, who was borne in the ancient and honorable Citie of Yorke.</p>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The Sun be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Virgo</hi> which is both a feminine ſigne, and the houſe of the feminine pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net <hi>Venus,</hi> they brought forth into the light Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to be the flower of the feminine ſexe.</note>MVſe ſing the Birth of lou'd <hi>Eliza's</hi> grace</l>
                  <l>The flowre of Virgins, whom the <hi>Virgin-ſigne</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When as the Sunne did there begin his race;</l>
                  <l>Sent to the light; both did their force combine</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Venus,</hi> who in that Signe hath her houſe</l>
                  <l>To grace vs with a Virgin vertuous.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Virgo</hi> is a ſigne encli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of body &amp; bountie of minde.</note>In this Signe <hi>Phoebus</hi> frames a louely face,</l>
                  <l>A comely feature, and a ſtature tall;</l>
                  <l>Vpon the heart he heaps his richeſt grace</l>
                  <l>Of prudence, knowledge, bountie; and withall,</l>
                  <l>Inclines to be kinde and officious,</l>
                  <l>ſhamefaſt, and graue, iuſt, and ingenuous.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>All which are further'd by the good aſpect</l>
                  <l>Of th'other ſtarres, which in that houre did ſhine</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:21"/>So happily; that we may well expect,</l>
                  <l>Of this choyſe wight, ſuch things as are diuine;</l>
                  <l>For they encline to magnanimity,</l>
                  <l>To gentleneſſe and liberalitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>The <hi>Horoſcope</hi> in <hi>Virgo</hi> wealth doth yeild,</l>
                  <l>For it diſpoſeth to be prouident,</l>
                  <l>In all things that belong to houſe or field,<note place="margin">Sol in Virgine Horoſcopans facit puellam ingenioſam, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erecundam, beneuolam, officioſam, prouidam, quae viro nubet circa <hi>16.</hi> annum &amp; parturiet primo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum eleganti forma.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To be thriftie, watchfull and diligent:</l>
                  <l>The maried ſtate, (if that the art be true)</l>
                  <l>Vnto her ſixteenth yeere is fit and due.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is ſubiect to her ſigne,<note place="margin">Theſe Cities are vnder the ſigne of <hi>Virgo</hi> vnder which Princeſſe <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> was borne.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Corinth</hi> and <hi>Rhodes, Pauie</hi> and <hi>Tholouſe</hi> Towne</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Baſil,</hi> with the braue <hi>Heidelberg</hi> of <hi>Rhine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Lyons</hi> Cities of Renowne:</l>
                  <l>And though I knowe not, which her muſt befall</l>
                  <l>Yet this I knowe that ſhe deſerues them all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Probus</hi> the Emperor was born the ſame month &amp; day that our <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba</hi> Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was borne on: he was a wight renowned for his notable parts of wiſedome, fortitude, valiancie and vigilancie in warre, wherein he was both foreward and fortunate, whereof read <hi>Vopiſcus</hi> and <hi>Cuſpinianus</hi> in his life.</note>
                  </head>
                  <l>Six Emperours <hi>Eliza's</hi> time did ſend</l>
                  <l>Into the light, two onely will I name</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Probus</hi> the prime of olde <hi>Romes</hi> princely men,</l>
                  <l>whoſe vertues worth did ſpread ech-where his fame:</l>
                  <l>The day and month of whoſe Birth was all one</l>
                  <l>With that of our braue <hi>Roſe</hi> of <hi>Albion.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12854:22"/>
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Maximilian</hi> the 2. the moſt worthie ſonne of a moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy father <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand</hi> the 1. was a Prince wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful wiſe iuſt, moderat, clement, milde, affable, and bountifull to Schollars and ſoldiours, of whom read in <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoria Augusta,</hi>
                     </note>The other is braue <hi>Maximilian</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whom men the ſecond of that name enſtile,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe worth went through all <hi>Germanie</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With <hi>Italie,</hi> through euery Land and Ile:</l>
                  <l>A Prince renown'd for his beneficence,</l>
                  <l>His wiſedome, Iuſtice and his temperance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fridericke</hi> the 1. and <hi>Fride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke</hi> the fifth Prince Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines of Rhine, were borne in the month of Auguſt the 1. on the 1. day, and the fifth on the foureteenth, whereof read <hi>Nicholaus Reuſnerus</hi> in his <hi>Diarium,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtinus Brunnius</hi> in his <hi>Catal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gus Electorum.</hi>
                     </note>To <hi>Caeſars</hi> two, two Princes we may ioyne</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſprung, and from the greateſt Kings,</l>
                  <l>Two <hi>Friderick</hi> Prince Palatines of <hi>Rhine;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>First,</hi> the <hi>Fift,</hi> whoſe fame with feather'd wings</l>
                  <l>Hee's far and wide, from filu'rie <hi>Thames</hi> to <hi>Tweede</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From fruitfull <hi>Kent</hi> vnto <hi>Kintires</hi> heede.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fredericke</hi> the firſt defended himſelfe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly againſt his many ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g enemies, Duks Marquiſes, and Earles, beſides Biſhops; hee tooke <hi>Charles</hi> Marquiſe of Baden, <hi>Vld<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ricus</hi> of Wirtemberg, <hi>Iohn</hi> Biſhop of Meaux, being all banded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in warlike manner and with them their whole Nobilitie, with fiue hundreth Knights, and carried them away captiue into his Citie of Heidelberg, and there kept them the ſpace of eleuen months, till at what time they had ranſomed themſelues whereof read <hi>Sebaſtianus Munſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s</hi> in his Germanie, <hi>Ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>us Wymp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>elingius,</hi> in his <hi>Epitome rerum Germanicarum;</hi> and <hi>Auguſtinus Brunnius</hi> in his Catalogue of the Palatine Princes.</note>9</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fred'rick</hi> the firſt call d the <hi>Victorious</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is magnified for his martiall deedes,</l>
                  <l>And proweſſe great; a Prince magnanimous</l>
                  <l>That of true worth, had both the fruits and ſeedes;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fred'rick</hi> the fift who now adornes this Ile</l>
                  <l>One day ſhall brooke firſt <hi>Fred'ricks</hi> honord ſtile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12854:22"/>
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eliza's</hi> birth was on <hi>S. Theclas</hi> day</l>
                  <l>That matchles matron,<note place="margin">Of <hi>S. Thecla</hi> the renowned Matrone and Martyr, read <hi>Euſebius, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agrius</hi> &amp; <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephorus</hi> Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories.</note> that rare Martyr'd wight</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe conſtant faith, and feruent zeale for ay</l>
                  <l>Shall be extoll'd, and had in honors hight:</l>
                  <l>And now me thinks her pietie and faith</l>
                  <l>Doe all reuiue in grac'd <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>Me thinks I ſee <hi>Eliza</hi> in her prime</l>
                  <l>Begin to follow the religious path</l>
                  <l>Of that Princeſſe ſtill honor'd to this time,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>S. Elizabeth</hi> daughter of <hi>Andrew</hi> King of Hungarie is much renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for her feruent pietie towards God and her cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie towards the poore whom ſhe liberally relieued; and the ſicke, vnto whom ſhee was wont with her owne hands to miniſter both medicine and meat, yea her coſtlieſt orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhe conuerted them to their vſe for the ſupplie of their wants, of whom read <hi>Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Montanus</hi> in her life.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Vnder the name of Saint <hi>Elizabeth:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who was the daughter of faire <hi>Hungarie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As ſhee's the daughter of great <hi>Britanie.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A parent to the poore <hi>Eliza</hi> was</l>
                  <l>Nine hundreth ſoules ſhe daily did maintaine</l>
                  <l>This worlds wealth ſhe did eſteeme but traſh,</l>
                  <l>True godlines was aye her greateſt gaine;</l>
                  <l>To faſt and pray, to helpe the poore in neede</l>
                  <l>To ſalue the ſicke, the fatherleſſe to feede.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>S. Hellene</hi> once a daughter of this Ile</l>
                  <l>King <hi>Coilus</hi> childe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>S. Helens</hi> day is the 18. of Auguſt, and our <hi>Eliza's</hi> birth-day the nineteenth.</note> and great <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Mother</l>
                  <l>Whoſe praiſe was ſpread from <hi>Caluarie</hi> to <hi>Kyle,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For piety was euen ſuch another:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12854:23"/>
                     <hi>Eliza's</hi> grace firſt ſaw faire <hi>Phoebus</hi> raye</l>
                  <l>The next vnto <hi>S. Helens</hi> holy day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>13</head>
                  <l>Great <hi>Ieſus</hi> grant to our <hi>Eliza's</hi> grace</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>S. Helens</hi> fortune, and her Empreſſe-fate</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">S. <hi>Helene</hi> the daughter of <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>us</hi> King of Britaines and the worthieſt Empreſſe that euer was in the world, ſo much renowned for her pietie, charitie and liberalitie: ſhee founded and builded about 32. Churches, ſhe liued the ſpace of 80. yeeres in health, wealth, with honors Imperiall hight, of whom read <hi>Euſebius, Nicephorus, Eutropius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Oroſius,</hi> in their Hiſtories.</note>That as they both are of the Royall race,</l>
                  <l>Of Britiſh Kings, ſo ſhe may imitate</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>S. Helens</hi> zeale, and ſo reape for her hyre</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Helens</hi> long life, <hi>Helens</hi> Crowne of Empire.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12854:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
